We have already had many episodes where we read assembler code and reverse engineered
我们已经看过很多集了，我们阅读汇编代码和逆向工程。
how a program works.
程序如何工作。
And we even have written our first exploit by using a buffer overflow vulnerability in
我们甚至编写了第一个利用缓冲区溢出漏洞的漏洞
a program written in C. In this episode I want to show you how you
一个用C语言写的节目。在这一集里，我想向你展示
can learn how to read assembler produced by C code yourself.
可以自己学习如何读取由C代码生成的汇编程序。
The idea is simple.
这个想法很简单。
Just write some C code with different C language features, and then look at the assembler code
只需编写一些具有不同C语言特性的C代码，然后查看汇编程序代码
that is produced by compiling it.
它是通过编译产生的。
This is often part of normal research.
这通常是正常研究的一部分。
For example listen to what Ian Beer from google project zero says during a talk about his
例如，听谷歌零号项目的伊恩·比尔在一次关于他的谈话中所说的话。
research on Inter Process Calls on OSX.
OSX进程间调用研究。
One approach to reversing, or to understanding how this kind of thing works would be to sit
要想扭转局面，或者理解这类事情是如何运作的，一个方法就是坐着
in IDA and just reverse the serialization and deserialization code, and slowly build
在IDA中，只需反转序列化和反序列化代码，然后慢慢构建
up a picture of how it works.
把它的工作原理拍下来。
But another kind of quite nice way to do it, is just, write a test program to send little
但另一种很好的方法是，编写一个测试程序来发送
messages and then find the right place using lldb to break and just start dumping hex.
然后使用lldb找到正确的位置，断开并开始转储hex。
So, because he had to understand a fairly complex data structure, he simply wrote a
因此，由于他必须理解相当复杂的数据结构，他只需编写一个
test program to analyse it, instead of reversing a full application.
测试程序来分析它，而不是反转一个完整的应用程序。
Or there was was a talk and paper from blackhat USA in 2007 about how to reverse C++ programs,
或者是在2007从黑头美国的一篇关于如何逆转C++程序的演讲和论文，
by looking at C++ concepts and how they look like in assembler.
通过查看C++概念以及它们在汇编程序中的样子。
So now I have created three different C code testcases and you can find them in my github
所以现在我已经创建了三个不同的C代码测试用例，您可以在我的Github中找到它们。
repository, or just write it yourself.
或者自己写。
One is about variables and datatypes.
一个是关于变量和数据类型。
One is about function calls.
一个是关于函数调用。
And one is about control flow stuff like loops and ifs.
一个是关于控制流的东西，比如循环和ifs。
So let’s start with the variables.c.
让我们从变量c开始。
First thing I want to point out are those triple Xs.
首先我要指出的是那些三重x。
Those triple Xs are defined as an assembler NOP instruction.
这些三重xs被定义为汇编程序nop指令。
The reason for that is, later when we look into the disassembly, we can find those NOPs
原因是，稍后当我们研究拆卸时，我们可以找到那些NOP
which are separating our tests, and that is pretty neat.
它将我们的测试分隔开，这非常好。
So this makes it easier to see which line of C Code is responsible for which lines in
所以这使得我们更容易看到C代码的哪一行负责其中的哪一行
assembler.
汇编程序。
I will not go over every single test, this is something you could do yourself.
我不会每次考试都复习，这是你自己能做的。
Simply pause the video at certain points or clone the repository.
只需在特定点暂停视频或克隆存储库。
Anyway.
不管怎样。
Let’s get started.
我们开始吧。
First of all you can see here a couple of simple numbers.
首先，你可以在这里看到几个简单的数字。
First we define a couple of numbers.
首先我们定义几个数字。
Unsigned and signed, integers and floating numbers.
无符号和有符号，整数和浮点数。
And different sizes with uint32 or uint64.
以及不同尺寸的uint32或uint64。
The latter is important, because normal Integers might have a different size depending on 32bit
后者很重要，因为正整数的大小取决于32位
or 64bit, so it can lead to bugs.
或者64位，这样就可以导致错误。
So better use datatypes you are guaranteed to get a certain size.
所以最好使用数据类型，这样可以保证获得一定的大小。
If you want to learn more about how to program C properly, there is a great blog entry called
如果你想进一步了解如何正确地编程C，有一个很棒的博客条目叫做
“How to C in 2015”.
“2015年如何实现C”。
After that we create an array with 32bit unsigned integers, and we access one element of this
然后我们创建一个包含32位无符号整数的数组，并访问其中的一个元素
array.
数组。
Then we look at a single character.
然后我们看一个角色。
And then also a string.
还有一根绳子。
And maybe you know that a star * means “pointer” in C. So we define a variable that is pointing
也许你知道星星*在c中的意思是“指针”，所以我们定义了一个指向
to a string.
一个字符串。
I have added a Makefile, so you can simply type `make` into the terminal to compile all
我添加了一个makefile，所以您可以简单地在终端中键入'make'来编译所有
files.
文件夹。
Or make clean to remove the binaries.
或者清除以删除二进制文件。
This will create a 32bit and a 64bit version of the variables program.
这将创建32位和64位版本的变量程序。
But as you can see, I get an error trying to compile a 32bit version with -m32 in this
但是正如你所看到的，我在编译32位版本时遇到了一个错误，其中包含了-m32
64bit machine.
64位机。
So I have to install the 32bit libraries first, to be able to build the code.
所以我必须先安装32位库，才能构建代码。
After installing those, the build works fine.
安装这些之后，构建工作正常。
A Makefile is just a little script that defines how a project has to be compiled.
makefile只是一个定义如何编译项目的小脚本。
So let’s open the code, 32bit and 64bit version next to each other in gdb and disassemble
那么让我们打开gdb中彼此相邻的代码、32位和64位版本并反汇编
main.
主要的。
And also open the code.
同时打开代码。
Ok now let’s look at the first integer examples with negative values and signed and unsigned
好了，现在让我们来看第一个带负值、有符号和无符号的整数示例。
values.
价值观。
First of all, all those local variables are stored somewhere on the stack, you can see
首先，所有这些局部变量都存储在堆栈的某个地方，您可以看到
that because they are referenced relative to the base-pointer.
因为它们是相对于基指针引用的。
Then you notice that the assembler code doesn’t know negative numbers.
然后您注意到汇编程序代码不知道负数。
They are fff something.
他们是FFF什么的。
If you are interested how negative numbers are displayed, watch my 10th episode about
如果你对负数的显示方式感兴趣，请看我的第10集
numbers.
数字。
And also there is no difference between variables that are signed or unsigned.
有符号变量和无符号变量之间也没有区别。
But there is one difference between the 32bit and the 64bit code.
但是32位代码和64位代码之间有一个区别。
Because we defined one number to be 64bit long, but on 32bit the registers are only
因为我们定义了一个64位长的数字，但是32位的寄存器只有
32bit.
32位。
So if you want to write full 64bit, you have to write two times.
所以如果你想写完整的64位，你必须写两次。
The floating point numbers are also interesting.
浮点数也很有趣。
Because they got stored somewhere else in the program.
因为它们被存储在程序的其他地方。
And that value is then moved into the local variable.
然后将该值移到局部变量中。
The array is also interesting.
这个数组也很有趣。
We created an array with 10 values but only set the first 5 values to a default value.
我们创建了一个有10个值的数组，但只将前5个值设置为默认值。
As you can see those values are stored on the stack.
如您所见，这些值存储在堆栈上。
And then it is moved from that location on the stack to the real array location.
然后将它从堆栈上的那个位置移动到实际的数组位置。
Instead of writing it directly to the array it does it this way.
它不是直接将它写到数组中，而是这样做的。
No idea why.
不知道为什么。
And you can see down here when we reference the 3rd entry.
当我们引用第三个条目时，您可以在下面看到。
So you can see that this is the real location of the array on the stack.
所以您可以看到这是数组在堆栈上的实际位置。
Next come the strings.
接下来是弦乐。
You can see that a character is just a byte.
您可以看到一个字符只是一个字节。
It doesn’t matter if we have an unsigned int with 8bit or a char.
如果我们有一个带8bit或char的无符号int，这无关紧要。
It’s the same.
是一样的。
And strings are also referenced over an address.
字符串也在地址上被引用。
So the local variable is not an array of charactes.
因此局部变量不是字符数组。
the local variable contains an address pointing to a string.
局部变量包含指向字符串的地址。
Now let’s have a look at the control_flows.
现在让我们看看控制流。
Open it in radare.
在Radare打开它。
Analyse all, seek to main function and enter Visual mode.
分析全部，寻找主要功能，进入视觉模式。
First we set a variable to zero.
首先，我们将变量设置为零。
And then comes the if.
然后是如果。
This is done by loading this local variable in a register and comparing to hex ff.
这是通过在寄存器中加载该局部变量并与hex ff进行比较来完成的。
And then jump if it was less or equal.
如果小于或等于，则跳。
So you can see which branch it may take.
所以你可以看到它可能需要哪个分支。
Then comes a while loop.
然后是一个小循环。
We load the local variable again in a register, compare it to a value, and either jump inside
我们在寄存器中再次加载局部变量，将其与一个值进行比较，然后跳进去
the block or leave.
要么封锁要么离开。
And inside the block we load this value again, increment it and write it back.
在这个块中，我们再次加载这个值，递增并写回它。
Now compare it to the foor loop.
现在将其与foor循环进行比较。
It’s basically the same!
基本上是一样的！
We start by setting the variable to 0.
我们首先将变量设置为0。
Then we compare if the loop condition is still true.
然后我们比较循环条件是否仍然是真的。
And inside the loop block, we can see our NOP.
在循环块中，我们可以看到我们的nop。
And at the end of the block we increment the variable by 1.
在块的末尾，我们将变量增加1。
Exactly the same like the while loop.
与while循环完全相同。
So you can see that a for and a while loop in C are basically the same.
所以你可以看到C中的a for和a while循环基本上是相同的。
Next let’s have a look at how functions are called.
接下来，让我们看看如何调用函数。
Again open both the 32bit and 64bit version.
再次打开32位和64位版本。
First thing you notice that the 64bit version moves a 0 in eax.
首先，您注意到64位版本在EAX中移动了0。
No idea why.
不知道为什么。
Otherwise the function call looks the same.
否则，函数调用看起来是相同的。
Except look at the addresses.
除了看看地址。
If you have no ASLR, then 64bit code is generally at hex 40 something.
如果没有aslr，那么64位代码通常是十六进制40左右。
While 32bit code is at hex 80 something.
32位代码是十六进制80左右。
Knowing stuff like that is helpful, because if you see an address with 40 something, you
知道这样的东西是有帮助的，因为如果你看到一个地址有40多岁，你
know immediately that it’s pointing into your code.
立即知道它指向您的代码。
So the next function returns a value and we save it in a variable.
所以下一个函数返回一个值，我们将它保存在一个变量中。
And you can see that in both cases, the value is taken from the eax register.
您可以看到，在这两种情况下，值都是从EAX寄存器获取的。
Ok, so apparently return values are handled via eax.
很明显，返回值是通过eax处理的。
Now function 3 is interesting, because we pass a parameter to it.
现在函数3很有趣，因为我们向它传递了一个参数。
In 32bit you can see that the value is loaded from somewhere and then stored on top of the
在32位中，您可以看到该值是从某个位置加载的，然后存储在
stack.
栈。
And then the function is called.
然后调用函数。
But on 64bit we see that the value is loaded into the edi register.
但在64位上，我们看到该值被加载到EDI寄存器中。
This is our first big difference.
这是我们的第一大区别。
Functions in 64bit seem to be called with parameters in registers, while in 32bit the
64位中的函数似乎是用寄存器中的参数调用的，而32位中的
parameters are stored on the stack.
参数存储在堆栈上。
Next function uses 2 parameters.
下一个函数使用两个参数。
And again, you can see how 32bit just places the value on the stack.
同样，您可以看到32位是如何将值放在堆栈上的。
First parameter on top of the stack, the second a bit further down.
第一个参数在堆栈的顶部，第二个参数在下面一点。
But in 64bit you can see that it uses esi and edi for that.
但是在64位中，您可以看到它使用ESI和EDI。
Now we get curious.
现在我们开始好奇了。
What does 64bit do when we have so many parameters, that we cannot keep them all in registers?
当我们有这么多参数，我们不能将它们全部保存在寄存器中时，64位会做什么？
First of all 32bit code again.
首先是32位代码。
You can see how the parameters are stored on the stack.
您可以看到参数是如何存储在堆栈上的。
And the first parameter is on top of the stack, and the last value moved.
第一个参数在堆栈的顶部，最后一个值被移动。
That’s what we would expect.
这就是我们所期望的。
In 64bit we can see that the first couple of parameters are stored in registers edi,
在64位中，我们可以看到前两个参数存储在寄存器edi中，
esi, edx, and so forth.
ESI、EDX等。
But from the 7th parameter on, they get stored on the stack as well.
但从第7个参数开始，它们也被存储在堆栈上。
Awesome!
令人惊叹的！
Now you can identify all kind of different assembler patterns.
现在您可以识别各种不同的汇编程序模式。
You don’t need a decompiler all the time.
你不需要一个反编译器。
You can do this all in your head.
你可以在脑子里做这一切。
And when you reverse more and more programs, those patterns become more easy to recognize,
当你逆转越来越多的程序时，这些模式变得更容易识别，
and you will not feel overwhelmed again with the mass of weird instructions.
你不会再被大量奇怪的指示所淹没。
You will be able to scan over a function and say: “ah here is a local variable.
您将能够扫描一个函数并说：“这是一个局部变量。
Then calls this other function with this variable as parameter.
然后用这个变量作为参数调用另一个函数。
And the return value is used in a loop”.
返回值在循环中使用。
And you can use the same method to understand how different disassemblers like hopper, radare,
你可以用同样的方法来理解不同的拆卸器，比如Hopper，Radare，
gdb display code.
GDB显示代码。
Or for example how different the at&amp;t assembler syntax is from the intel syntax.
或者例如，AT&T汇编程序语法与Intel语法有多大不同。
I hope you have a lot of fun next time reversing a program.
我希望你下次能有很多乐趣来改变计划。